<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>On Digitizing Historic Music Storage Media For Computational Analysis</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Khulusi</surname>
                        <forename>Richard</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Image and Signal Processing Group, Computer Science, Leipzig University, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>khulusi@informatik.uni-leipzig.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Fricke</surname>
                        <forename>Heike</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Research Center Digital Organology, Musical Instrument Museum, Leipzig University</affiliation>
                    <email>heike_marianne.fricke@uni-leipzig.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Fuhry</surname>
                        <forename>David</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Research Center Digital Organology, Musical Instrument Museum, Leipzig University</affiliation>
                    <email>david.fuhry@uni-leipzig.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Piontkowitz</surname>
                        <forename>Vera</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Research Center Digital Organology, Musical Instrument Museum, Leipzig University</affiliation>
                    <email>vera.piontkowitz@uni-leipzig.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Focht</surname>
                        <forename>Josef</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Research Center Digital Organology, Musical Instrument Museum, Leipzig University</affiliation>
                    <email>Josef.Focht@uni-leipzig.de</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2022-03-23T14:11:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>DH2022 Local Organizing Committee</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>7-3-1, Hongo, </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Japan</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>DH2022 Local Organizing Committee</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords n="category" scheme="ConfTool">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords n="subcategory" scheme="ConfTool">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords n="keywords" scheme="ConfTool">
                    <term>Historic Musical Storage Media</term>
                    <term>Visual Analysis</term>
                    <term>Musicological Analysis</term>
                    <term>Digitization</term>
                    <term>MIDI</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords n="topics" scheme="ConfTool">
                    <term>Global</term>
                    <term>Europe</term>
                    <term>English</term>
                    <term>19th Century</term>
                    <term>20th Century</term>
                    <term>Contemporary</term>
                    <term>data</term>
                    <term>object</term>
                    <term>and artefact preservation</term>
                    <term>music and sound digitization</term>
                    <term>encoding</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>Computer science</term>
                    <term>Musicology</term>
                    <term>I plan to attend the conference in Tokyo in person</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div rend="DH-Heading1" type="div1">
                <head>Introduction </head>
                <p>Between 2018 and 2020, the digitization project TASTEN, funded by the German
                    government, digitized 3200 piano rolls for self-playing pianos preserved at the
                    Musical Instruments Museum at Leipzig University (MIMUL). A piano roll is a historic
                    music storage media (MSM) coding movement impulses through holes punched into
                    paper (Focht, 2020). When played, a pneumatic system uses this code to create
                    sounds at runtime.
                    For musicologists, such piano rolls are of high value. First, they are the only source of
                    musical performances by famous pianists in times preceding sound recording
                    technologies. Secondly, for researchers they offer a rich repository to study the
                    music-making practice and musical interpretation around 1900. We expand our prior
                    source catalogue to include their technical predecessors: Cardboard and metal plates,
                    which also use punched holes as code (Focht, 2021). They share the issue of being
                    fragile – after decades of usage and storage – making it important to digitize them
                    for preservation, also.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div rend="DH-Heading1" type="div1">
                <head>Related Work </head>
                <p>We found a lack of publications dealing with challenges, issues, and processing of MSM in general. This may be due to most of such projects being on a small scale in
                    private settings (pianola.co.nz, 2021; IAMMP, 2021). Scientific publications are
                    presented by Debrunner (2013), who developed a scanner capable of reading
                    information directly from piano rolls and dealing with paper based distortion issues,
                    for a single format (Welte piano rolls). Shi et al. (2019) built an online database of almost 500 digitized
                    piano rolls offering representations including images, audios, and MIDI files, focusing
                    only on the same format.
                    No published scientific or private projects are to be found concerning metal or
                    cardboard plates and their digitization.
                </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic height="9.233958333333334cm" n="1001" rend="inline" url="Pictures/6892e6f7baf681be247f60f5399a989f.png" width="15.980833333333333cm"/>
                <head rend="Subtitle" style="text-align: center; ">Figure 1: </head><p>Pipeline of the digitizing of piano rolls and plates through different processing steps and manual input of a Musicologist</p></figure>
                
            </div>
            <div rend="DH-Heading1" type="div1">
                <head>Digitizing MSM</head>
                <p>While prior projects show great results in digitizing piano rolls, processes capable of
                    dealing with multiple formats of piano rolls and plates in general are non-existent.
                    Furthermore, digitizing is only the first step for musicologists. This data allows them
                    to answer research questions by reading and hearing the encoded works which are
                    difficult to impossible to read. Additionally, these processes allow for distant reading
                    analysis and comparative approaches.
                    We propose a workflow (Figure~1) capable of digitizing all 3,200 piano rolls of 30
                    different formats available in the MIMUL. Currently, work is done to include more
                    than 25 formats of 438 plates.
                    The workflow begins with a conservator-led cleaning process to protect the objects
                    and the researchers. Damages which would lead to the destruction of the object
                    were documented. Next, metadata like weight, measurements, format, title,
                    composer, and performer was extracted to be included in our research tool
                    musiXplora. For the actual digitizing, a scanning company was commissioned, for which we constructed an unwinding mechanism, making it possible to create a single
                    scan of the piano rolls (as 300dpi .tif images, resulting in up to 5.000x550.000 pixels and up to 5GB).
                    While the prior project (TASTEN – 2018-2020) generated scans of piano rolls, the
                    current DISKOS project focuses more deeply on musicologists’ research questions.
                    Examples would be “How did composers play their own compositions on the piano?”,
                    or “Can the computer use this digital knowledge to identify which pianist played a
                    piano roll of unknown origin?” Also, exploration and visual analysis of the objects can
                    be offered through distant reading visualization systems embedded in the
                    musiXplora.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div rend="DH-Heading1" type="div1">
                <head>Technical Details</head>
                <p>Starting with the preprocessing of the backlit images the actual process labels
                    connected components (musical notes) on the image and applies filtering to keep
                    only the components representing notes. Calculating the distance from each hole to
                    the edge of the medium and using mean shift clustering we can assign each note to
                    its respective track. We finally apply corrections to account for empty tracks and
                    distortions and calculate the position and width of each hole. Combining this
                    information with an expert created mapping of tracks to MIDI notes, we can then
                    generate a MIDI file accurately representing the information on the medium.
                    Relevance for Musicology
                    These files allow users to work interactively with the music and help musicologists in
                    their work with these sources. Furthermore, this offers an enhanced experience for
                    museum visitors, by making it possible to voice the digitized piano rolls and plates
                    using the digital representation of keyboard instruments created during TASTEN.
                    Hence, historic media can be experienced on historic instruments even if the physical
                    instruments would not have been interoperable.
                    For the musicologists, these results offer a way to open up previously unreadable
                    sources. Besides close reading approaches, the generated data allows for distant
                    reading (visualization) methodology and novel research questions like examining
                    which schools of interpretation and playing techniques are represented and how they
                    have spread between performers. 
                    Further, these results are also important for educational and playful aspects like
                    listening to these historical virtuous interpretations without risking the media and
                    instruments.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div rend="DH-Heading1" type="div1">
                <head>Limitations</head>
                <p>As we are in the first of three project years, some challenges still exist: The image
                    processing results are highly dependable on a suitable preprocessing, which differs
                    quite a lot even between different formats of the same media type. Metal plates in
                    particular are operated under pressure during playback. While the playback
                    instruments themselves are constructed to negate this deformation, a plain
                    photography of the media does not lead to correct results and needs a semi-manual
                    correction process. In general, we are content with our results for cardboard plates
                    and piano rolls of specific formats, but are aware of needed improvements.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div rend="DH-Heading1" type="div1">
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>Even with the best preservation techniques, most materials deteriorate from
                    humidity and stress through time. Hence, valuable information stored on analog
                    media is prone to damage and even loss. Such information includes original
                    recordings of famous virtuosos like Edvard Grieg, not only valuable as music
                    recording, but also important for musicologists interested in analyzing playing
                    techniques and differences between musical notation and interpretation by their
                    composers. To allow digital processing of such media, digitization is mandatory. We
                    present a pipeline taking image sources of circular and linear played storage media
                    and creating digital representations in form of MIDI files, which then can be analyzed,
                    further processed, edited, or even played through modern and historical instruments.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:13.5pt">pianola.co.nz</hi>
                        <hi xml:space="preserve" style="font-size:13.5pt">(2021): Saving the Music of Yesterday. </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:13.5pt">http://www.pianola.co.nz/public/index.php</hi> (Accessed: 01 January 2022)
                        </bibl><bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve" style="font-size:13.5pt">Comaniciu, D., &amp; Meer, P. </hi>
                        <hi xml:space="preserve" style="font-size:13.5pt">(2002). Mean shift: A robust approach toward feature space analysis. </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:13.5pt">IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence</hi>, 24(5), 603–619. https://doi.org/10.1109/34.1000236
                        </bibl><bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:13.5pt">Debrunner, D.</hi>
                        <hi xml:space="preserve" style="font-size:13.5pt"> (2013). Von der Welte-Rolle zu parametrisierbaren Wiedergabe auf synthetischen Instrumenten und MIDI-fähigen Selbstspielklavieren. </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:13.5pt">In C. E. Hänggi &amp; Köpp (Eds.), Recording the Soul of Music: Welte-Künstlerrollen für Orgel und Klavier als authentische Interpretationsdokumente.</hi>
                        </bibl><bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:13.5pt">Focht, J.</hi>
                        <hi xml:space="preserve" style="font-size:13.5pt"> (2020). </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:13.5pt">MusiXplora</hi>. https://musixplora.de/mxp/2002522 (Accessed 01 January 2022)
                        </bibl><bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:13.5pt">Focht, J.</hi>
                        <hi xml:space="preserve" style="font-size:13.5pt"> (2021). </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:13.5pt">MusiXplora.</hi>
                        https://musixplora.de/mxp/2003518 (Accessed 01 January 2022)
                        </bibl><bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:13.5pt">IAMMP</hi>
                        <hi xml:space="preserve" style="font-size:13.5pt">(2021). </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:13.5pt">International Association of Mechanical Music Preservationalists</hi>. http://www.iammp.org/ (Accessed 01 January 2022)
                        </bibl><bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:13.5pt">Pedregosa, F., Varoquaux, G., Gramfort, A., Michel, V., Thirion, B., Grisel, O., Blondel, M., Prettenhofer, P., Weiss, R., Dubourg, V., Vanderplas, J., Passos, A., Cournapeau, D., Brucher, M., Perrot, M., Duchesnay, E.</hi>
                        <hi xml:space="preserve" style="font-size:13.5pt"> (2011). Scikit-learn: Machine Learning in Python. </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:13.5pt">Journal of Machine Learning Research</hi>, 12, 2825–2830.
                        </bibl><bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:13.5pt">Shi, Z., Sapp, C. S., Arul, K., McBride, J., &amp; Smith III, J. O.</hi>
                        <hi xml:space="preserve" style="font-size:13.5pt"> (2019). Supra: Digitizing the Stanford University Piano Roll Archive. </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:13.5pt">In A. Flexer, G. Peeters, J. Urbano, &amp; A. Volk (Chairs), ISMIR, Delft</hi>.
                        </bibl><bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:13.5pt">van der Walt, S., L. Schönberger, J., Nunez-Iglesias, J., Boulogne, F., D. Warner, J., Yager, N., Gouillart, E., Yu, T.</hi>
                        <hi xml:space="preserve" style="font-size:13.5pt"> (2014). scikit-image: Image processing in Python.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:13.5pt">PeerJ</hi>
                        <hi xml:space="preserve" style="font-size:13.5pt"> 2:e453 https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.453</hi>
                        </bibl><bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:13.5pt">The ImageMagick Development Team.</hi>
                        <hi xml:space="preserve" style="font-size:13.5pt">(2021). </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:13.5pt">ImageMagick</hi>. Retrieved from https://imagemagick.org (Accessed 01 January 2022)
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
